The following content is provided under a
Creative Commons license. Your support will
help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to offer
high -quality educational resources for
free. To make a donation or to view
additional materials from hundreds of MIT
courses, visit MIT
OpenCourseWare at ocw .mit .edu.
So I've got a little list of things I'm
hoping to do today. I'll begin with a few
final words about saddle points. The reason
I'm interested in saddle points is when we
get to this deep
learning direction,
you know that the big step there is finding
a minimum of the total cost function and
gradient descent, which we'll certainly
discuss is the usual method, or stochastic
gradient descent. And all kinds of issues
arise. What happens if you have a saddle
point?
Or a degenerate minimum? All these
possibilities and the understanding of deep
learning is focusing more and more on
what does that gradient descent algorithm
produce. I just thought,
minima and maxima we know about. Saddle
points are kind of a little hazier, right?
So this is a perfect example, and I'll just
say a few more words about it. Then I want
to talk about the lab 3 that I boldly
posted on Stellar. And also about projects,
just to get us thinking about those. And
then my real math topic for today and this
week is basic ideas of statistics,
particularly the covariance matrix. I'm
sure you've met mean and variance. Those
are the most used words, and we'll use them
again. But then I want to go on to
covariance. OK, so that's what's coming
today. A few words on saddle points, a lot
of words about the lab, and anything you
can want to ask about projects, and then
some basic statistics. OK, saddle point. So
the example I'm taking
is this Rayleigh quotient.
And I'm taking a simple matrix S. I might
as well take a diagonal matrix, because
it's symmetric, of course. And any
symmetric matrix, I could just change
variables by a Q matrix, an orthogonal
matrix, to get to something like that. And
then the x, we're in 3D. So we've got a
sort of manageable size here. And the x
vector is uvw. So this is the quotient.
x transpose x, you see, is just exactly 5u
squareds, 3v squareds, and 1w squared. And
I divide by the length to normalize things.
So what are the main facts that we know
that I'm not going to prove? But what are
the main facts? What's the maximum value of
r? What's the minimum value of r, of that
function? And is there a
saddle point? So saddle
of r. OK, what's the maximum value? How
large could you make that ratio, capital R?
I just think this isn't a standard topic
in 1806. But with an example like this,
you'll see the whole point.
OK, so how large could I make r?
Yeah, go ahead and say it. Sigma 1. But
what is it here? Let's just do with these
numbers. How big can I make that ratio, r?
And what choice of uvw makes it big? So how
big I can get it is? 5. That ratio can't be
more than 5. You see it would be 5. Well,
how do I get to 5? Maximum of r is 5. And
what is the uvw that at? So I'll say at.
What choice of uvw would give us 5
here? You see it immediately, 1, 0, 0.
And what about the minimum of r? The
minimum of this ratio. How do I make that
ratio small? Well, I load stuff onto w
instead of loading it up onto u. Right?
It's clear. So what is the minimum value of
r? 1. Because I'll load everything into w.
So the minimum value will be 1. And that
will be at the vector 0, 0, 1. I've loaded
everything there. And then the point of
this short discussion is, is there another
place where the derivatives, first
derivatives, of r are all 0? That's where,
of course, the first derivatives are 0 at
the max, at the min. But we have three
variables here. And we're going to find the
third point. And what is that point? You
probably guess. And what will be the saddle
value? So you have to see some kind of a
surface that, I guess, what are we in?
4d. So we have vectors. We have base
coordinates uvw. And r goes vertically. And
we plot that surface. And we don't really
understand it, unless we think a lot about
it, which we haven't. But we can pretty
well guess what's what. So what do you
think is the saddle value? And where is it
going to be reached? Everybody's going to
tell me correctly. Saddle value would be 3
at this middle point.
OK. And what are these three with respect
to the matrix? They're its eigenvectors.
What are these three numbers with respect
to the matrix? These are its eigenvalues.
It's just like that's why that Rayleigh
quotient is such an important function.
It's kind of a messy function. If you take
its derivative, you know, you've got to use
a quotient rule or use a Lagrange
multiplier to make it. That's the way to
make it more manageable. But it's kind of
messy. But the results could not be better.
The values there are the eigenvalues.
And the places where you reach them are the
eigenvectors. And so the max is the most
important. So that's sigma 1. Here's sigma
3, or lambda and sigma, because the matrix
is symmetric positive definite. And here in
the middle is sigma 2. And if
we want to compute eigenvectors,
which I'm not planning to do today just to
make this remark, computing eigenvectors,
getting the largest one or the smallest one
is a lot quicker in general than getting
these ones in the middle. You have to use
good codes and pay attention to computing
those saddle point values. So is there
anything nice I can do with saddle point?
How does one think about saddle points?
So again, saddle point is defined by first
derivatives
equals 0. And the
second derivatives,
OK, so that's a matrix. Here's a vector,
the gradient vector. The derivative with
respect to u, the derivative with respect
to v, and dr, dw, just a vector. And all
those components are 0. The gradient vector
is 0. But what about second derivatives?
Well, that's getting more. There are nine
of those now, because I've got r, u, u,
second derivative with respect to u,
second. But I've got mixed derivatives,
second derivative of r with respect to du,
dv. So I have a 3 by 3 matrix. Fortunately,
that matrix is symmetric, because we're
blessed by that wonderful fact that the
derivative with respect to u and then v
is the same as v and then u. So we get a
symmetric matrix.
And it's, well, I won't write it down. But
it's going to have a, you know, it's got
the maximum, minimum, and saddle
information built in. Here's this one
additional thought that I want to
communicate about saddle points.
Because it's really nice to somehow get
back to maxima and minima. So the idea of
this idea for a saddle point is to be able
to write it as the maximum of a minimum. In
a way, yeah. So let me do
that. And then I'm all done. OK.
So that value is the maximum of over
something of the minimum over something of
x transpose of our function.
OK. Now, of course, I have to tell you
what you're maximizing over and what you're
minimizing over. But that's the idea, is
that one way to get into that middle place
there where the saddles are sitting is to
have a maximum of a minimum. And that
leads, this what I'm about to complete
here, would lead you, for example, very
quickly to the interlacing theorem
that I spoke about for eigenvalues and for
singular values of when you perturb s or
when you throw away a row and column of s.
The eigenvalues go in between. That is the
kind of conclusion that this max min stuff
is set up to produce. So here, let me just
tell you what it would be. I'm aiming to
get lambda 2. OK. So I'm going to take a
maximum over 2D, two -dimensional spaces,
subspaces of R3. We're in 3D.
So you can see that sort of like two
-dimensional spaces. Let me give that
subspace a name like v. Yeah, that'll do.
Cap v, everybody can see that that's a cap
v. And then this will be the
minimum over v. So it's kind of tricky.
So I take any subspace that's two
-dimensional. And I'll take one in a
moment. And I'll figure out the minimum.
Well, suppose I take the subspace v, which
is spanned by the first two. It's supposed
to be a 2D subspace. Spanned by the first,
suppose I try example here. Example. The
span of 1, 0, 0 and 0, 1, 0. OK. In other
words, all vectors u, v, 0. That's
a 2D space. What is the minimum
of that Rayleigh quotient over that two
-dimensional space? So now I'm taking a
minimum. I don't have to think about saddle
points. So I'm in all. So I'm looking at
the thing. But w is 0 now. Everybody sees
that I've squeezed it down to 2D. So w is
0. So what is the minimum now? So this
thing would become, for this space, would
become the 5u squared and the 3v squared
over the u squared plus the v squared. But
the w is 0. So what's the minimum of
that? 3. 3. OK. The minimum is 3 for this
particular space. Let
me call it v special.
For that particular space, the minimum is
3. Correct? Everybody sees that. Because I
just have u and v to play with, the 5 and
the 3. So if I put everything into v, I get
the 3. And now I take the maximum. So I've
learned that this, so the maximum is at
least 3. Because this particular choice of
v gave me the answer 3. And now I'm taking
the maximum of all possible 2D spaces.
And I'll certainly, I got 3 for one of the
possible spaces of v. And I might get
higher than 3 for some other one. But
actually, I don't. The truth is that this
turns out to be 3, which is, of course,
exactly what we wanted. So I'm saying that
this particular 2 -dimensional space, the
minimum over that, minimum, the minimum
there is 3. And now I maximize over all
others. And so the idea is that for any
other one, the minimum value will be below
3. And therefore, when I go for the max
of the mins, I get 3. So I just repeat that
and then be quiet about this whole subject.
So it's a maximum over subspaces of a
minimum of the Rayleigh quotient. If that
subspace is exactly the perfect choice,
this one, I get the value 3. And I'm
claiming that's the biggest value I can
get. Because if I pick any other subspace,
what if I picked a subspace that, suppose,
another v would
be all vectors 0vw?
What would be the minimum? What would I get
for the minimum of this thing? But now w
is in the picture. And u is not in the
picture. What would I get for the minimum
there? 1. I'd get 1. The minimum would be
when I put everything into w and I got 1.
And then when I take the max, it's not a
winner. It's thrown out. The winner will be
that space and the 3. So I guess I'm hoping
that you sort of see in this small example
that you can express this middle saddle
value as a it's reasonable to think of it
as a maximum in some directions and a
minimum in another. Think of the, well, try
to think of some surface which is going
up in some directions. So it's a minimum in
those directions. And it's going down
in other directions. So it's a max in those
directions. And the saddle point is perched
in there at that, right at that place at
the saddle point. You know, if you're
like hiking from here to California or
something, you're going to pass a saddle
point. Actually, you see it on the mass.
The Mass Pike has an amazing little sign.
I don't know if you've noticed it. If you
drive west on the Mass Pike, pretty
far west of Boston, there's a little sign
telling you the altitude or elevation,
whatever. And it says there, this is the
highest point until you reach the Rockies,
basically. That seemed like, OK. Midwest is
pretty flat, right?
Because that's a long way away. You don't
think of Massachusetts as like really in
the big league with high spots. But there
it is. It's the highest one until you get,
and I think it tells you where the next one
will be in Colorado. Anyway, those highest
points are tend to be saddles. The
very, very highest point, where is that? In
Alaska or somewhere. That's a max, of
course, by definition. But there are a lot
of saddle points in other places. And those
would be maxima of minima or minima of
maxima. Good. I'm stopping there. We
might see this again when we start gradient
descent.
But at least, because saddle points
don't come up much in teaching calculus, I
thought that was good. OK.
Second point is models, lab 3,
and projects, anything you'd like to
ask about projects. So please, this is your
chance to ask. You
could also ask by email.
Idea for a project, let me encourage you or
a team to work on it or just yourself. And
if you want to think, OK, shall I get some
feedback of does this sound sensible, any
suggestions, send me an email. Yeah. I'll
be happy to. Because I'm a total beginner
here, too. When I
created this lab 3,
I was desperate. Not for model 1. For model
1, have you looked at the, it's online,
it's reached stellar. And it's only one
printed page. But people had a look at
this. So I'll just repeat quickly. Model 1
is an example of overfitting. And what's
going on with model
1? So model 1 says take
5 would be enough. But I probably said 10
or something. So I'll make it 6 points. And
put approximate, put a curve through them.
So if you put a curve, and the curve is
going to be a polynomial. So
we're going to fit by polynomial.
Everybody knows polynomial
is C0 plus C1x plus whatever.
Ckx to the k, let's say.
For k equals 0, well, I don't know if I
even asked 0. That would be the best
straight line. That would be run along
the average. k equal to 1, that would be a
straight line fit. And you would compute
that by least squares. Because of course,
no straight line is going to go through
all the points. You're going to have some
error by least squares. 2 would be fitting
by a parabola. Again, you'll have some
error, but smaller, since parabolas include
straight lines. So we reduce the total sum
of squares error by going to degree 2,
degree 3, and up to how many points? So we
take 1, 2. Let me just use
the same letter I've used here.
Probably have, oh. Well, the m is the
number of points. But m varies between one
point, I guess, and probably n. Points.
Yeah. Or maybe k here. Up to n. Up to 6,
let's say. OK. And I want to make a comment
about 6. No, 5 would do it. Won't. Degree
5 will fit the 6 points. We've got 6 points
here. But if I stop at degree 5, I was
better there. Because degree 5 polynomial
also has a constant term. So it really has
6 coefficients. So there's a degree.
There's a 1 degree 5 polynomial with 6
numbers, 6 coefficients, that goes through
those 6 points. So it's a perfect fit. That
would be an exact fit of the data. So
here's the data. Create a polynomial of
degree 5 that goes through those points
exactly and look at the result. And what
would you see if you look at the result?
Would it be smooth? Of course. It's a
polynomial. Would it be nice? No. It'll be
horrible. To get through those points, did
I get 6 points? Yeah. To get through those
points, I'm guessing that that fifth degree
polynomial, the perfect fit, is an example
that occurs to practically everybody of
overfitting. Because making that decision,
perfect fit, learn the data, training data
exactly, will send a polynomial. I don't
know what it looks like. I don't want to.
Well, I do want to know, but
not right now. Anyway, craziness.
Of course, I'm going to ask. It doesn't
look like that, probably. I'm going to ask
you to plot the results. What's the least
squares error when you fit by a straight
line, when you fit by a horizontal line, a
constant, fit by a straight line, move up
to parabolas, move up to cubics? But when
you hit this, you're not making any error
at all. You're not really needing to use
least squares. You can solve Ax equal b, Ac
equal b equals b. So this is the b thing.
And c is the vector of coefficients. And
the matrix A is bad news when it's 6 by
6, when you get up to a complete fit. And I
guess what I wanted just to see is, a lot
of things I don't know. Suppose I change 6
to 20 or something. Then I'm pretty sure
that out there at 18, 19, 20, this thing is
really off the map.
And you could
compute its max. And you'd see a very
big number. But I don't know where. But of
course, for a straight line, that would
be pretty safe. The slope would be pretty
moderate. And I don't know where you. So
that's probably underfitting, to try to fit
this by a straight line. It's not as close
as you would want. But fitting by a full
perfect fitting, it's a high degree
polynomial, is certainly overfitting. Where
is the boundary? I'm sure people know about
this. But I think it is something we could
learn from.
So that's what that model 1 is about. And
just to make one final comment, that matrix
A has a name in the case where it's
a square matrix, where you're fitting
exactly, interpolating would
be the word. So that exact fit,
that corresponds
to square matrix A.
And the word for
it is interpolation.
And I guess it's Lagrange again,
seeing that guy too often here. The
Lagrange interpolation. But the matrix has
a different name. And whose
name is associated with that matrix?
Vandermonde. Vandermonde. So this is the
square matrix, which was, so let me write
it. This is called a
Vandermonde matrix.
And it's a matrix that has a crazy large
inverse. Because just as I'm saying, the C
that comes out from the perfect fit, from
the interpolation, from the square matrix,
the C is going to be giant. And so you
could write, you'll be able to, you will
construct a matrix, of course, to do this.
And it will be identical to the, so we've
heard this word Vandermonde matrix
in this class within the last week. Anybody
remember where the word Vandermonde came
up in class? It was in Professor Townsend's
lecture.
It was in his video, if you wanted, as an
example of a matrix which had a horrible
inverse, a giant matrix. The Hilbert matrix
was another example. I think he did two
examples, Vandermonde and Hilbert. So this
Vandermonde matrix, I could write it down,
but I'll leave that to you, has a big
inverse. And its eigenvalues, well, no,
singular values, it's not symmetric. Its
singular values are way scattered. It has
tiny little singular values, plus an
ordinary size singular values. So that's
the example that I just think you could go
with. And as far as I can see, sending it
to autograder as a Julia file, it'll be
even worse than usual, sending it to
autograder. They won't, I think it wouldn't
know what to do, as far as I can see. So
I'm thinking of some submissions coming to
Gradescope. And I'm thinking of some plots
to show what happens as k increases, and
some tables of data, maybe, and then maybe
a paragraph of conclusion, like what degree
is safe. And when does it become risky,
and when does it become disaster? So stuff
like that. It's really, these are sort of
open -ended labs, and you use any language.
Questions about that example? Which is
really, that's what I'm expecting to
be ready, and quite a good example for
Wednesday after the break.
Question or, anyway, you could email
me. You should probably see what the model
looks like. Then the second one, I've taken
a first jump into networks. Made a very
simple network without a lot of, without
any hidden layers at all, actually. And
just wrote down what I think might work.
But you may find that you want to modify
model 2, go for it. I don't have any patent
or personal stake in the way model 2 is
written. But the idea is fit data. And
well, start with data. But don't make it
too perfect, because we don't want, we want
some learning to happen here. And so it's
the classification problem. So it won't be
least squares with variables like u and v
and w. It's just plus 1 or minus 1,
or 1, 0, or cat and dog, whatever the
classification is. So that's the basic,
basic problem to start with in deep
learning. For quite a long time, that's the
natural problem. So it's a classification
problem. And the description here suggests
one way to set up the training data.
And execute a neural net -like experiment,
but without getting very far away from
ordinary linear algebra. Yeah. So if you
want to, as I say, if you want to change
this, develop it further,
get some ideas about it, that's what,
that's what the whole point is here.
Actually, the faculty meeting on this week,
maybe today, what's today? Wednesday?
Yeah, so it's this afternoon. Faculty
doesn't come too much, but of course, it's
late in the afternoon. But faculty meeting
this afternoon is about MIT's plans for
requirements or courses in computational
thinking. And in a way, this course within
the math department is among the ones that
are in that direction. Of course, in other
departments, those are
further along. Anyway,
when Raj Rao taught the course last spring,
he had the Julia system better developed.
And it was a chance to bring computers and
bring laptops and do things in class. And
you'll have that chance again
when he visits in a month.
OK, enough. And I'm open to questions about
the project. Maybe ask you to email me a
rough idea of a project. And tell me if
you were in a group or if you would like to
find a group of maybe two or three people.
I'm not thinking of groups of 50. Two or
three would be sensible.
Questions about projects? I mean, I just
introduced this idea of a project. And I
apologize for it. Not bringing it up
the first week. But I just couldn't see. I
don't want to do exams on linear algebra.
We've passed that point. So this seemed the
right way to go. But I'm not looking for
a PhD thesis here. Questions? Thoughts?
I guess I hope you know you can ask. Yeah,
oh, good. So could you maybe describe the
scope of the project? The scope does not
mean . GILBERT STRANGER. Right. How will I?
I think, yeah, so the scope is connected to
the time that you would devote to it. And
what should I say about scope? Maybe the
equivalent of three homeworks or something?
Because I'd give an idea that
it's not infinite, but it's not something
tiny and trivial. Yeah, go ahead. Do you
have any example projects? Or past years?
GILBERT STRANGER. Well, that's the thing.
There aren't really past
years. We are the ones.
So I will have next year if you
contribute some good ideas.
Maybe I should ask Professor Rao to maybe
send us the projects he uses in Michigan.
That would be some ideas. But remember
that he hasn't, up to now anyway, moved the
course toward deep learning. He did other
topics, all of which would be fine. But
then quite a few people have had some
6036 or know something about convolutional
neural nets. And I'm certainly excited to
get to that topic. So the project could get
there or it could not. Both totally fine.
OK, that's a good idea. I'll ask Raj for
just the projects and you'll recognize a
couple because you've done a couple. But
there are a bunch more. Yeah. Yeah, then
there was another question or thought. And
I'm remembering that there was, I think
maybe everybody got an email or a stellar
announcement that some members of the class
took an initiative, which was wonderful,
to open the possibility of people just
showing up an evening a week in the Media
Lab, was it? Or was there a location? And
has it happened? Or is it a future event?
It happened. It happened. OK. But people,
I hadn't mentioned it in class. So probably
you didn't have and were not really into
projects yet. So it was probably a quiet
evening. Yeah. Yeah. And that's productive
but quiet. OK. So will it happen again?
Sure. I think maybe now we'll be looking
after spring break. After spring break. OK.
So post again on Stellar the plan for the
next meeting that people could come to. So
this is David Anderton. So you'll recognize
his name. And did you have the meeting in
the Media Lab? Yeah, we had it on the
Thursday and the Friday. OK. So with the
break coming and spring hopefully coming
after today's potential storm, yeah, when
we come back, good. OK. Is that good? I
hope some of that is helpful. You get an
idea. You're seeing about as much as
I know, which is model one is definitely
doable. And very significant. And van
der Maan matrices and so on are truly
important. And their
instability is a big issue.
But then moving toward weights and training
data and test data is where we want to go.
Good. So do I have some time? I do. Just
to speak about mean and variance, the two
golden words of statistics, and covariance,
the matrix, the intersection of linear
algebra with statistics. And then some
famous inequality. So I'll continue with
this on Friday and post some of the
material. So that's coming from a later
section of notes. OK.
So what is the mean? So I
have n possible outcomes
with those probabilities.
And I can ask you
about the sample mean.
Or I can ask you about
the expected mean. OK.
So the sample means we've done an
experiment. We've got some output. The
expected mean means we know probabilities,
but we haven't used them yet. So this uses
actual output. And the sample
mean is simply, shall I just say,
m for mean? Well, these two are importantly
different. One is something where you've
done the experiment. And this is before
you do the experiment. And the letters get
maybe mu. I'll change to mu.
I don't want to use s because s gets
used with variance. OK. So it's just the
average. Average
output from the sample.
So like I flipped a coin a million times,
and the output was 0 or 1. So I got a
million 1s and 0s. And I take the average.
And I'm expecting a number like half a
million because I'm thinking of a fair
coin. And the law of large numbers would
say that this sample mean does approach
1 half. With probability 1 as the number of
samples gets larger. So sample mean is
straightforward. The expected mean means
we, these are actual
sample outputs.
They happened. Whereas the expected
mean is just the, and I'll use m for that.
The probability of the first output times
that output plus the probability of the
second output times that output plus plus
pn xn. OK. So it's the, that will approach
that with probability 1 as this number,
capital N. Notice the difference. Capital N
here is the number of samples, the number
of trials. And it gets big. We keep doing
things more and more. This is just,
this little n is the number of possible
different outputs with their probabilities.
And there you see it. And of course, in
the continuous case, we would
take the integral of x, p of x dx.
So let me just, by analogy, you should know
what the continuous version is and what
the discrete version is. That's the mean.
OK. Now for variance. Sample variance.
And shall I say expected variance? I don't
know. Just variance is what people would
usually say.
I don't know if I've remembered the right
word there. Sample variance. It's a, what
is that? I included this topic in the
linear algebra book. Anyway, yeah. OK. So
what's the sample variance?
So I guess I'm, whew. Yeah. So what is the
sample variance? What's the variance about,
anyway? What's the key point of variance?
It's the distance from the mean. So it'll
be, this will be a distance from the sample
mean. And this will be a distance from the
expected mean.
So not distance from 0, but distance from
mu and m, from the center of the thing. OK.
So the sample variance. So again, we have
n samples. But for some wonderful reason in
statistics, you divide by n minus 1 this
time. And the reason has to do with the
fact that you used 1. This will involve
the mean. So this would be the first output
minus mu squared up to the
nth output minus mu squared.
So it's the average distance from mu,
average squared distance from mu, but with
this little twist that, of course, when
n is large, it's not a very significant
difference between n and n
minus 1. I think that's about right.
All this is that I'm just doing one
experiment over and over. Covariance,
which is the deeper idea. The deeper idea
is where linear algebra comes in. I have a
matrix. Because why? Because I'm doing
several, multiple experiments at the same
time. I'm flipping two coins. I'm flipping
15 coins. I'm doing other things. So that
will be covariances, when I'm doing several
experiments at once. That will involve
matrices of that size.
That's the variance. I should have given
you the usual notation, the expected value
of x. That's what's the mean. And here I'm
looking at the expected value of what? So
when I'm computing a variance using
probabilities, so I'm using expectations,
not trial runs. Expectations means use the
probabilities. And what is the expectation
of the distance from x
to the mean squared?
And that is, when I'm doing an expectation
for a discrete set, I think of the
probability, the first probability,
that goes with an output x1
and a second probability that goes with an
output x2. And each time, I subtract from
the mean and square. So that's the variance
that everybody calls sigma squared.
Now, two minutes left is enough to say two.
A few more words about covariance. Oh, to
get to covariance, I really have to speak
about joint probabilities. That's a key
idea, joint probabilities. So I'm
doing two experiments at once.
So each one has its own probabilities. But
together, I have to ask, so here are two
easy cases. Suppose I'm flipping two coins.
So I might get heads, heads. I may get
heads, tails, tails, heads, or tails,
tails. Four possibilities, four possible
outputs there, four possible pairs. And if
you're flipping one coin and I'm flipping
another one, those are independent results.
Those are independent results. There won't
be a covariance where some, where by
knowing what my flip was, I would know more
about your flip.
But now, the other possibility
would be to glue the coins together.
Now, if I do a flip, they always come up,
heads and heads or tails and tails. So the
heads, tails combination is not possible.
In fact, one output is totally dependent on
the other output. So that's the other
extreme. We have independent outputs with
covariance 0. And we have totally dependent
outputs when the things are just glued
together, when one result tells us what the
other result is. Then that situation where
the covariance is a maximum. Couldn't
be bigger than that. If you were polling a
family, say political polling, well, there
would be some covariance expected there.
The two or three or five people living in
the same house wouldn't be independent,
entirely independent. But they, nor would
they always say all five give the same
answer. So the covariance matrix would be,
have some off diagonal, but it would still
be not invertible. And actually, what I
want to tell you about next time at the
start is that covariance matrix, which I
have to define for you, will be symmetric
positive definite. Or semi -definite.
What's the semi -definite case? Of course,
that's the case where the coins are glued
together. OK, thanks. So you know what's
coming Friday. I know that holiday is also
coming Friday. And you'll make a good plan.
And I'll move on
after the break. Good.